Guide to the Sarah Josepha Hale Papers, 1850-1877 (bulk 1863-1867)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Sarah Josepha Hale Papers
1850-1877
1863-1867
Hale, Sarah Josepha Buell, 1788-1879
0.4 cubic feet (2 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Thirty original letters by Hale and typescript copies of letters to and from Hale (originals also available) concerning the inclusion of the word "female" in Vassar Female College, women's education, other business of Vassar College, missionary work, and women in the church. Other correspondents include Milo P. Jewett, Benson J. Lossing, John H. Raymond, and Matthew Vassar.
Biographical Note
Sarah Josepha Buell was born in Newport, N.H., on October 24, 1788. She married David Hale, a lawyer, in 1813 and they had five children. Widowed in 1822, she turned to writing to earn a living. She published several books of verse and a novel, Northwood, in the 1820's, and became editor of the Ladies' Magazine in 1828. She had high standards as an editor, and the magazine reflected her interests, primarily what she called the "women's sphere;" she was opposed to woman's suffrage but was a great proponent of education for women and the kindergarten movement. In 1837 she became editor of Godey's Lady's Book, a magazine which made a practice of avoiding the controversial issues of the day. Despite these somewhat conservative views, she was committed to advancing the interests of women--her efforts on behalf of Vassar College are reflected in this group of letters. In the 1850's she became interested in careers for women--such as medicine, foreign missionary work. Sarah Hale, however, should be remembered not primarily as a feminist but as a highly skilled editor. She did not retire from Godey's until she was ninety; she died in Philadelphia the following year, 1879.
Scope and Content Note
Thirty original letters by Hale and typescript copies of letters to and from Hale (originals also available) concerning the inclusion of the word "female" in Vassar Female College, women's education, other business of Vassar College, missionary work, and women in the church. Other correspondents include Milo P. Jewett, Benson J. Lossing, John H. Raymond, and Matthew Vassar.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Separated Materials
Folders 4-63 are typescripts, originals are in the Autograph File.
Subject Headings
Names:
Jewett, Milo P.; Lossing, Benson J. (Benson John), 1813-1891; Raymond, John H. (John Howard), 1814-1878; Vassar, Matthew, 1792-1868
Organizations:
Vassar College; Vassar Female College
Subjects:
Women's colleges--New York (State)--Poughkeepsie; Women--Education; Women--Employment; Women and religion; Women in missionary work; Editors
VCL Categories
Education; Religion; Vassar College; Women's History
Encoding Information
Encoded by Elizabeth Clarke, April 2007.
Series List
- Series I. Correspondence from Hale, (Box 1)
- Series II. Correspondence to Hale, (Box 2)
Container List
- Correspondence from Hale
  - to Horace Greeley, 2 September 1850 (Folder 1.1)
  - to Milo P. Jewett, 17 February 1864 (Folder 1.2)
  - to Pliney Earle, n.d. (Folder 1.3)
  - to Horace Greeley, 2 September 1850 (Folder 1.4)
  - to Matthew Vassar, 30 April 1860 (Folder 1.5)
  - to Matthew Vassar, 5 April 1861 (Folder 1.6)
  - to Benson Lossing, 21 December 1863 (Folder 1.7)
  - to Milo P. Jewett, 17 February 1864 (Folder 1.8)
  - to Milo P. Jewett, 20 February 1864 (Folder 1.9)
  - to Matthew Vassar, 19 March 1864 (Folder 1.10)
  - to John H. Raymond, 6 June 1864 (Folder 1.11)
  - to John H. Raymond, 21 June 1864 (Folder 1.12)
  - to John H Raymond, 3 November 1864 (Folder 1.13)
  - to Matthew Vassar, 21 January 1865 (Folder 1.14)
  - to Benson Lossing, 6 February 1865 (Folder 1.15)
  - to Benson Lossing, 6 February 1865 (Folder 1.16)
  - to John H. Raymond, 24 February 1865 (Folder 1.17)
  - to Benson Lossing, 25 February 1865 (Folder 1.18)
  - to John H. Raymond, 2 March 1865 (Folder 1.19)
  - to John H. Raymond, 8 March 1865 (Folder 1.20)
  - to Matthew Vassar, 30 March 1865 (Folder 1.21)
  - to Benson Lossing, 4 April 1865 (Folder 1.22)
  - to Benson Lossing, 30 March 1865 (Folder 1.23)
  - to John H. Raymond, 5 April 1865 (Folder 1.24)
  - from Matthew Vassar [unclear if there was a to MV as of 1 May 2014], 7 June 1865 (Folder 1.25)
  - to John H. Raymond, 8 August 1865 (Folder 1.26)
  - to Benson Lossing, 26 August 1865 (Folder 1.27)
  - to Martin B. Anderson, 14 June 1866 (Folder 1.28)
  - to Matthew Vassar, 2 December 1867 (Folder 1.29)
  - to Matthew Vassar, 27 March 1868 (Folder 1.30)
  - to John H. Raymond, 31 March 1871 (Folder 1.31)
  - to John H. Raymond, 12 February 1875 (Folder 1.32)
  - to John H. Raymond, 18 June 1877 (Folder 1.33)
  - to John H. Raymond (Folder 1.34)
  - to Matthew Vassar, n.d. (Folder 1.35)
- Correspondence to Hale
  - from Matthew Vassar, 8 May 1860 (Folder 2.36)
  - from Matthew Vassar, 11 December 1862 (Folder 2.37)
  - from Henry W. Lee, 21 December 1863 (Folder 2.38)
  - from Milo. P Jewett, 17 February 1864 (Folder 2.39)
  - from Matthew Vassar, 31 March 1864 (Folder 2.40)
  - from Milo P. Jewett, 2 May 1864 (Folder 2.41)
  - from Matthew Vassar, 8 June 1864 (Folder 2.42)
  - from Matthew Vassar, 26 September 1864 (Folder 2.43)
  - from Matthew Vassar, 26 December 1864 (Folder 2.44)
  - from John H. Raymond, 26 October 1864 (Folder 2.45)
  - from Matthew Vassar, 7 June 1865 (Folder 2.46)
  - from Matthew Vassar, 28 August 1865 (Folder 2.47)
  - from Matthew Vassar, 28 October 1865 (Folder 2.48)
  - from Matthew Vassar, 4 December 1865 (Folder 2.49)
  - from Matthew Vassar, 4 December 1865 (Folder 2.50)
  - from Matthew Vassar, 29 January 1866 (Folder 2.51)
  - from Matthew Vassar, 27 June 1866 (Folder 2.52)
  - from Matthew Vassar, 25 August 1866 (Folder 2.53)
  - from Matthew Vassar, 5 December 1866 (Folder 2.54)
  - from Matthew Vassar, 22 February 1867 (Folder 2.55)
  - from Matthew Vassar, 7 March 1867 (Folder 2.56)
  - from Matthew Vassar, 22 March 1867 (Folder 2.57)
  - from Matthew Vassar, 20 June 1867 (Folder 2.58)
  - from Matthew Vassar, 20 June 1867 (Folder 2.59)
  - from Matthew Vassar, 11 July 1867 (Folder 2.60)
  - from Matthew Vassar, 9 September 1867 (Folder 2.61)
  - from Matthew Vassar, 3 October 1867 (Folder 2.62)
  - from Pliny Early, n.d. (Folder 2.63)